[
    {
        "question": "1) What is Ruby programming language?",
        "answer": "Ruby is a dynamic, reflective, general purpose, open source programming language that focuses on simplicity and productivity. Ruby has a mixed features of Perl, small talk, Eiffel, Ada and Lisp. Ruby was designed to create a new language which makes a balance with the functionality of Imperative languages.\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "2) Who is the developer of Ruby?",
        "answer": "Ruby is designed and developed by Yukihiro \"martz\" Matsumoto in mid 1990 in Japan.\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "3) Why Ruby is known as a language of flexibility?",
        "answer": "Ruby is known as a language of flexibility because it facilitates its author to alter the programming elements. Some specific parts of the language can be removed or redefined. Ruby does not restrict the user. For example, to add two numbers, Ruby allows to use + sign or the word 'plus'. This alteration can be done with Ruby's built-in class Numeric.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "4) List some features of Ruby?",
        "answer": "Ruby has many features. Some of them are listed below.\nADVERTISEMENT\nObject-oriented\nFlexible\nDynamic typing and Duck typing\nGarbage collector\nKeyword arguments\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "Similarities:\nHigh level language\nSupport multiple platforms\nUse interactive prompt called irb\nServer side scripting language\nDifferences:\nRuby is fully object oriented while Python is not.\nRuby supports EclipseIDE while Python supports multiple IDEs.\nRuby use Mixins while Python doesn't.\nRuby supports blocks, procs and lambdas while Python doesn't.\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "ruby -v\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "7) What are class libraries in Ruby?",
        "answer": "Ruby class libraries contain variety of domain such as thread programming, data types, various domains. Following is a list of domains which has relevant class libraries:\nText processing\nCGI Programming\nNetwork programming\nGUI programming\nXML programming",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "Operators are a symbol which is used to perform different operations.\nUnary operator\nAirthmetic operator\nBitwise operator\nLogical operator\nTernary operator\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "9) What is RubyGems in Ruby programming language?",
        "answer": "RubyGems provides a standard format for distributing ruby programs and libraries. It works as a package manager for the Ruby programming language.\nRubyGems is now a part of the standard library from Ruby version 1.9.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "Ruby variables hold data which can be used later in a program. Each variable act as a memory and shas a different name.\nThere are four types of variables in Ruby:\nLocal variable\nClass variable\nInstance variable\nGlobal variable\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "11) What is the difference between nil and false in Ruby?",
        "answer": "nil false\nnil cannot be a value. false can be a value.\nnil is returned where there is no predicate. in case of a predicate, true or false is returned by a method.\nnil is not a boolean data type. false is a boolean data type.\nnil is an object of nilclass. false is an object of falseclass.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "Ruby data types represent type of data such as text, string, numbers, etc.\n\nThere are different data types in Ruby:\nNumbers\nStrings\nSymbols\nHashes\nArrays\nBooleans\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "13) What is the use of load and require in Ruby?",
        "answer": "In Ruby, load and require both are used for loading the available code into the current code. In cases where loading the code required every time when changed or every times someone hits the URL, it is suggested to use 'load'.\nIt case of autoload, it is suggested to use 'require'.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "The Ruby if-else statement is used to test condition. There are various types of statement in Ruby.\nif statement\nif-else statement\nif-else-if (elsif) statement\nternary statement\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "In Ruby, we use 'case' instead of 'switch' and 'when' instead of 'case'. The case statement matches one statement with multiple conditions just like a switch statement in other languages.\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "Ruby for loop iterates over a specific range of numbers. Hence, for loop is used if a program has fixed number of itrerations.\nRuby for loop will execute once for each element in expression.\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "Ruby while loop is used to iterate a program several times. If the number of iterations is not fixed\nfor a program, while loop is used.\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "Ruby do while loop iterates a part of program several times. In this, loop will execute at least once because do while condition is written at the end.\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "Ruby until loop runs until the given condition evaluates to true. It exits the loop when condition becomes true. It is opposite of the while loop.\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "Ruby break statement is used to terminate a loop. It is mostly used in while loop where value is printed till the condition is true.\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "Ruby next statement is used to skip loop's next iteration. Once the next statement is executed, no further iteration will be performed.\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "Ruby redo statement is used to repeat the current iteration of the loop. The redo statement is executed without evaluating loop's condition.\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "Ruby retry statement is used to repeat the whole loop iteration from the start.\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "Ruby comments are non-executable lines in a program. They do not take part in the execution of a program.\nSingle line comment syntax:\n#This is single line comment.  \nMulti line comment syntax:\n=begin  \nThis  \nis  \nmulti line  \ncomment  \n=end  \nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "Object is the default root of all Ruby objects. Ruby objects inherit from BasicObject which allows creating alternate object hierarchies.\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "26) How to create Ruby object?",
        "answer": "Objects in Ruby are created by calling new method of the class. It is a unique type of method and predefined in Ruby library.\nADVERTISEMENT\nSyntax:\nobjectName=className.new  \nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "Each Ruby class is an instance of Ruby class. Classes in Ruby are first class objects. It always starts with a keyword class followed by the class name.\nSyntax:\nclass ClassName  \ncodes...  \nend  \nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "Ruby method prevent us from writing the same code in a program again and again. Ruby methods are similar to functions in other languages.\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "To use a Ruby method, we need to first define it. It is defined with def and end keyword.\nMethod name should always start with a lowercase letter.\nSyntax:\ndef methodName  \ncode...  \nend  \nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "Ruby code blocks are called closures in other programming languages. It consist of a group of codes which is always enclosed with braces or written between do...end.\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "A block is written in two ways:\nMulti-line between do and end\nInline between braces {}\nBoth are same and have the same functionality.\nFor more information: Click here\nsyntax:\n\nblock_name{  \nstatement1  \nstatement2  \n..........  \n}  \nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "The yield statement is used to call a block within a method with a value.\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "The &block is a way to pass a reference (instead of a local variable) to the block to a method.\nHere, block word after the & is just a name for the reference, any other name can be used instead of this.\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "Ruby module is a collection of methods and constants. A module method may be instance method or module method. They are similar to classes as they hold a collection of methods, class definitions, constants and other modules. They are defined like classes. Objects or subclasses can not be created using modules. There is no module hierarchy of inheritance.\nModules basically serve two purposes:\nThey act as namespace. They prevent the name clashes.\nThey allow the mixin facility to share functionality between classes.\nSyntax:\nmodule ModuleName  \nstatement1  \nstatement2  \n...........  \nend  \nModule name should start with a capital letter.\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "Ruby doesn't support multiple inheritance. Modules eliminate the need of multiple inheritance using mixin in Ruby.\nA module doesn't have instances because it is not a class. However, a module can be included within a class.\nWhen you include a module within a class, the class will have access to the methods of the module.\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "Ruby string object holds and manipulates an arbitary sequence of bytes, typically representing characters. They are created using String::new or as literals.\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "You can access Ruby string elements in different parts with the help of square brackets []. Within square brackets write the index or string.\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "Writing multiline string is very simple in Ruby language. We will show three ways to print multiline string.\nString can be written within double quotes.\nThe % character is used and string is enclosed within / character.\nIn heredoc syntax, we use << and string is enclosed within word STRING.\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "39) What is the use of global variable $ in Ruby?",
        "answer": "The global variable is declared in Ruby that you can access it anywhere within the application because it has full scope in the application. The global variables are used in Ruby with $ prepend.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "Ruby concatenating string implies creating one string from multiple strings. You can join more than one string to form a single string by concatenating them.\nThere are four ways to concatenate Ruby strings into single string:\nUsing plus sign in between strings.\nUsing a single space in between strings.\nUsing << sign in between strings.\nUsing concat method in between strings.\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "In most programming languages strings are immutable. It means that an existing string can't be modified, only a new string can be created out of them.\nIn Ruby, by default strings are not immutable. To make them immutable, freeze method can be used.\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "42) In how many ways you can compare Ruby string?",
        "answer": "Ruby strings can be compared with three operators:\nWith == operator : Returns true or false\nWith eql? Operator : Returns true or false\nWith casecmp method : Returns 0 if matched or 1 if not matched\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "43) What are class libraries in Ruby?",
        "answer": "Ruby class libraries contain variety of domain such as thread programming, data types, various domains. Following is a list of domains which has relevant class libraries:\nText processing\nCGI Programming\nNetwork programming\nGUI programming\nXML programming",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "44) What are Ruby arrays and how they can be created?",
        "answer": "Ruby arrays are ordered collections of objects. They can hold objects like integer, number, hash, string, symbol or any other array.\nIts indexing starts with 0. The negative index starts with -1 from the end of the array. For example, -1 indicates last element of the array and 0 indicates first element of the array.\nA Ruby array is created in many ways.\nUsing literal constructor []\nUsing new class method\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "?",
        "answer": "Ruby array elements can be accessed using #[] method. You can pass one or more than one arguments or even a range of arguments.\nSyntax:\n#[] method  \nMethods used to access Ruby elements:\nat method\nslice method\nfetch method\nfirst and last method\ntake method\ndrop method\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "46) In how many ways items can be added in an array in Ruby?",
        "answer": "Ruby array elements can be added in different ways.\npush or <<\nunshift\ninsert\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "47) In how many ways items can be removed from array in Ruby?",
        "answer": "Ruby array elements can be removed in different ways.\npop\nshift\ndelete\nuniq\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "A Ruby hash is a collection of unique keys and their values. They are similar to arrays but array use integer as an index and hash use any object type. They are also called associative arrays, dictionaries or maps.\nIf a hash is accessed with a key that does not exist, the method will return nil.\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "49) How to create a new time instance in Ruby?",
        "answer": "A new Time instance can be created with ::new. This will use your current system's time. Parts of time like year, month, day, hour, minute, etc can also be passed.\nWhile creating a new time instance, you need to pass at least a year. If only year is passed, then time will default to January 1 of that year at 00:00:00 with current system time zone.\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "What are the ways to define ranges?",
        "answer": "Ruby range represents a set of values with a beginning and an end. They can be constructed using s..e and s...e literals or with ::new.\nThe ranges which has .. in them, run from beginning to end inclusively. The ranges which has ... in them, run exclusively the end value.\nRuby has a variety of ways to define ranges.\nRanges as sequences\nRanges as conditions\nRanges as intervals\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "51) What are Ruby iterators?",
        "answer": "Iterator is a concept used in object-oriented language. Iteration means doing one thing many times like a loop.\nThe loop method is the simplest iterator. They return all the elements from a collection, one after the other. Arrays and hashes come in the category of collection.\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "52) How many iterators are there in Ruby?",
        "answer": "Following iterators are there in Ruby:\neach iterator\ntimes iterator\nupto and downto iterator\nstep iterator\neach_line iterator\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "53) Name different methods for IO console in Ruby?",
        "answer": "The IO console provides different methods to interact with console. The class IO provides following basic methods:\nIO::console\nIO#raw#raw!\nIO#cooked\nIO#cooked!\nIO#getch\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "54) How to open a file in Ruby?",
        "answer": "A Ruby file can be created using different methods for reading, writing or both.\nThere are two methods to open a file in Ruby.\nFile.new method : Using this method a new file can be created for reading, writing or both.\nFile.open method : Using this method a new file object is created. That file object is assigned to a file.\nDifference between both the methods is that File.open method can be associated with a block while File.new method can't.\nSyntax:\nf = File.new(\"fileName.rb\")  \nOr,\nFile.open(\"fileName.rb\", \"mode\") do |f|  \nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "55) How to read a file in Ruby?",
        "answer": "There are three different methods to read a file.\nTo return a single line, following syntax is used.\nSyntax:\nf.gets  \ncode...  \nTo return the whole file after the current position, following syntax is used.\nSyntax:\nf.rea  \ncode...  \nTo return file as an array of lines, following syntax is used.\nSyntax:\nf.readlines  \n[code...]",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "Ruby class libraries contain a variety of domains like thread programming, data types, and various domains. It has additional libraries evolving day by day. The following are the domains which has relevant class libraries.\nText processing: File, String, Regexp for quick and clean text processing.\nCGI Programming: There are supporting class library for CGI programming support like, data base interface, eRuby, mod_ruby for Apache, text processing classes.\nNetwork programming: Various well-designed sockets are available in ruby for network programming.\nGUI programming: Ruby/Tk and Ruby/Gtk are the classes for GUI programming\nXML programming: UTF-8 text processing regular expression engine make XML programming very handy in ruby.",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "57) What is sysread method in Ruby?",
        "answer": "The sysread method is also used to read the content of a file. With the help of this method you can open a file in any mode.\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "58) How will you rename and delete a file in Ruby?",
        "answer": "Ruby files are renamed using rename method and deleted using delete mehtod.\nTo rename a file, following syntax is used.\nSyntax:\nFile.rename(\"olderName.txt\", \"newName.txt\")  \nTo delete a file, following syntax is used.\nSyntax:\nFile.delete(\"filename.txt\")  \nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "59) How to check whether a directory exist or not in Ruby?",
        "answer": "To check whether a directory exists or not exists? Method is used.\nSyntax:\nputs Dir.exists? \"dirName\"  \nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "Ruby exception is an object, an instance of the class Exception or descendent of that class. When something goes wrong, Ruby program throws an exceptional behavior. By default Ruby program terminates on throwing an exception.\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "",
        "answer": "Built-in subclasses of exception are as follows:\nNoMemoryError\nScriptError\nSecurityError\nSignalException\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "62) How an exception is handled in Ruby?",
        "answer": "To handle exception, the code that raises exception is enclosed within begin-end block. Using rescue clauses we can state type of exceptions we want to handle.\nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "63) Explain the use of retry statement in Ruby?",
        "answer": "Usaually in a rescue clause, the exception is captured and code resumes after begin block. Using retry statement, the rescue block code can be resumed from begin after capturing an exception.\nSyntax:\nbegin  \ncode....  \nrescue  \n# capture exceptions  \nretry # program will run from the begin block  \nend  \nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    },
    {
        "question": "64) Explain raise statement in Ruby?",
        "answer": "The raise statement is used to raise an exception.\nSyntax:\nraise  \nOr,\nraise \"Error Message\"  \nOr,\nraise ExceptionType, \"Error Message\"  \nOr,\nraise ExceptionType, \"Error Message\" condition  \nFor more information: Click here",
        "reference": "javatpoint.com",
        "role": "ruby"
    }
]